<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The YnoGuy</title>
    <description>Wine+Software by Bill Langley</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 23:51:45 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 23:51:45 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tale of Two Counties. Napa vs. Sonoma. Part 8.</title>
        <description>&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/the-magnificent-seven-1200-1200-675-675-crop-000000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Magnificent 7&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-magnificent-7&quot;&gt;The Magnificent 7&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/tale-of-two-counties-p7/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I discussed the rise of the Gallo wine empire and its significance in re-introducing wine to Americans post prohibition. However, Gallo and its competitors were predominately in the low cost “jug” wine business. The few consumers seeking higher quality were mainly located in the metropolitan east coast and were buying well established European brands. However, as early as the 1950s a handful of individuals in California were experimenting with French varietals in the quest to make wines of a quality that matched their Euro-rivals. I will focus this post on 7 individuals in particular that set early ground on the state–and indeed world’s–wine renaissance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/171112-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;André Tchelistcheff&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;André Tchelistcheff (1901-1994)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;andré-tchelistcheff&quot;&gt;André Tchelistcheff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A discussion of Napa wine history without mentioning the “Maestro” would be equivalent to reciting French history without Napoleon Bonaparte. In Napa his name is as famous as it is difficult to pronounce. Just as it was in the wine boom of the 1850s and 60s, the success of the Californian wine industry would depend on the education and experience brought by immigrants. Arguably the earliest post prohibition premium wine producers in Napa was Beaulieu Vineyards (BV). Established before prohibition, founder Georges de Latour dedicated himself to producing wines that would rival those from his French homeland. Shortly after the repeal, de Latour traveled to France in search of an educated winemaker. The Russian born Tchelistcheff was already being courted by owners worldwide, but de Latour gave him an offer he couldn’t refuse as vice president and chief winemaker at BV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;God made Cabernet Sauvignon, whereas the Devil made Pinot Noir. - André Tchelistcheff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon his arrival in 1938, Tchelistcheff put an immediate focus on Cabernet Sauvignon paying particular attention to the nuances of the grape’s development in the relatively warm, dry climate of Napa Valley. However, his real contributions to the California wine industry didn’t start until after Latour’s death in the 1950’s. Georges’ widowed wife Fernande proved less interested in making wine than making money and stifled many of Tchelistcheff’s efforts to improve quality. Frustrated, André began assisting other winemakers in the valley including Mike Grgich, Joe Heitz, and Robert Mondavi. After retiring from BV in 1973 he became a consulting enologist for Jordan Vineyard and ran his own private wine lab offering advice extending out to new up-and-coming regions in Oregon and Washington. André’s contributions and accolades are too many to list, but here are some notables:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noted the advantages of cold fermentation as it relates to the acidity and fruitiness of a wine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first winemaker to use American oak.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helped develop ways to control malolactic fermentation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Studying, developing many US wine regions including Carneros, Willamette Valley, and Columbia Valley.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recognized by Wine Spectator in 2000 as “The Person Who Has Done the Most to Advance Wine Quality.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lee-stewart&quot;&gt;Lee Stewart&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J. Leland Stewart never like the pretense of having lineage to the Lelands of Stanford University fame, which is why he went simply by the name “Lee”. In 1943 he bought thirty acres of land on Napa’s Howell mountain for the purpose of agriculture. However unlike his prune-producing neighbors, Lee’s desire was to plant vines and start a winery that he would name Chateau Souverain (a play on the French “sovereign”). Without the benefit of any experience or education in viticulture or enology Lee relied predominately on observations and experimentation–with a sharp focus on consistency. In the lore of Napa wine personalities Lee Stewart is arguably the least known, but I find him an integral part in what were the earliest days of modern wine history. As other aspiring–and often clueless–wine makers arrived in Napa in the 1960s, they could look to Lee as one of the few able to offer them advice. His willingness to do so, along with André Tchelistcheff, Louis Martini, and Robert Mondavi fostered a trend of collaboration over the years to come that would be a key to Napa’s success vs. other regions. Lee’s biggest claim to fame was his hiring of Mike Grgich, immigrating him to the US, and thus launching the career of what would be another Napa legend. However, he deserves many other lesser known accolades:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduced and named varietal Petit Sirah (later recognized as French varietal Duriff).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early advocate of “clean wine making practices” introducing hygienic practices that would only be adopted around the world decades later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Championed Martin Ray’s philosophy of single-varietal winemaking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outspoken proponent of practicing the French standard of fermenting Chardonnay &lt;em&gt;sur-lee&lt;/em&gt; in oak barrels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By 1963 Chateau Souverain would win 93 medals at the California State Fair. Then the standard for judging quality California wine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/0fed4221e9b0b6f9475a02c6cb3f3c56-articleLead.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Miljenko “Mike” Grgich&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Miljenko “Mike” Grgich. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.palmspringslife.com&quot;&gt;– © Palm Springs Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mike-grgich&quot;&gt;Mike Grgich&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well known as an irascible curmudgeon from Croatia, the name Mike Grgich (Miljenko Grgić) seems to be at the center of any major conversation in the wine industry throughout the second half of the 20th century. Like his mentor Tchelistcheff, his route to the US was circuitous coming from war-ravaged and communist Eastern Europe. First hired by Lee Stewart at Chateau Souverain, Grgich went on to work for Tchelistcheff at BV, then Chateau Montelena, Christian Brothers, and Robert Mondavi before partnering with Austin Hills (Hills Brothers Coffee) to start his own winery Grgich Hills. In the 80’s and 90’s Grgich was recognized as one of the “big 3” Chardonnay producers along with Far Niente and ZD Wines. Together they set the standard for a style of richness that set Napa apart. Recently, Grgich’s contribution to the famous Chardonnay that one the Paris Wine Tasting of 1976 was smeared by the movie &lt;em&gt;Bottle Shock&lt;/em&gt; which falsely portrayed owner/partner Pat Barret as the winemaker. Although, initially consulted by the movie’s producers, rumor has it Grgich’s famously abrasive behavior got him kicked off the set and ultimately written out of the script. Of the 5 people I mention in this post Grgich is the soul survivor at 95 and is easily recognizable wearing his signature beret. Like his mentor Tchelistcheff, Grgich’s accolades are overwhelming, but here’s just a few:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Winemaker of the winning Chardonnay in the famous Paris Wine Tasting of 1976.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His first vintage at Grgich Hills won the 1980 Chardonnay Showdown over 221 entries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inducted into the Culinary Institute’s Vintner’s Hall of Fame&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Beard Award winner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;louis-p-martini&quot;&gt;Louis P. Martini&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his youth the shy, introverted Louis P. Martini stood in the shadow of his gregarious bigger than life father Louis M. Martini. Louis M. followed the same risks and path of Cesare Mondavi during prohibition by getting out of the grape business and into winemaking. Louis M. always believed prohibition was an aberration and so started his winery in 1922. Son Louis P. took over in 1946 and set about focussing on making high quality wine. Luckily, his father had purchased some choice acreage around Napa and bordering Sonoma to work with, including Monte Rosso on the back side of Mt. Veeder which, IMHO produces some of the best Cabernets. Starting in 1962 Louis P. ventured further a field east to Chiles Valley and Carneros in the south. Carneros, in particular, was frowned upon as a wine region at the time. However, around 1973 Louis P. started to recognize the success of Pinot Noir in his Carneros vineyards. At that time Pinot was commonly grown along with Zinfandel and Cabernet in the hotter Napa Valley. Then, California Pinot was gritty and heavy in body like any other red. Martini was one of the first to recognize it’s elegance when grown in cooler climates like the foggy bay-hugging Carneros district. Today, Carneros is the only region where Napa County still grows Pinot Noir. Both father and son were active in their small Napa wine community. Louis M. helped found the Napa Valley Vintners Assoc. Louis P. served on the Wine Advisory Board. Both were advocates for collaboration in the valley. Here are some of Louis P.’s accomplishments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to plant grapes in Carneros.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to produce a vintage Merlot in California.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early advocate and grower in the Sonoma’s Russian River Valley.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early proponent of mountain vineyards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inducted into the Culinary Institute’s Vintner’s Hall of Fame.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG-cr-sm-1919x799.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jack and Jamie Davies&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jack and Jamie Davies. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.schramsberg.com&quot;&gt;– © Schramsberg Vineyards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jack-davies&quot;&gt;Jack Davies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s not surprising that a high society couple out of Beverly Hills might have a taste for Champagne, it’s arguable whether they would have the grit and wear-with-all to actually make it. Jack and Jamie Davies were partners and I am being remiss—if not sexist—for omitting Jamie’s name from the header, but this is a post about individuals and Jack was the winemaker. The Davies were bit by the “back to nature” bug and in 1965 bought an old ghost winery once owned by a German immigrant named Jacob Schram back in the late 1800’s. Unlike most old wineries, this one was unique in that Schram had hewed a cave into the Diamond Mountain hillside property. This suited Jack as he was not here to make still wines like most of his neighbors. The Davies were interested in making sparkling wine that rivaled vintage Champagne. This meant growing the same grapes, adhering to Champagne’s &lt;em&gt;Methode Traditionale&lt;/em&gt; winemaking process, and riddling/aging wine in caves. Despite his ambitions, Jack was not an accomplished winemaker. Luckily, neighbors like Louis Martini, André Tchelistcheff, and the Mondavi brothers were so enamored with the idea of world class sparkling being made in Napa Valley they chipped in to help Jack figure it out. Initially word was slow, but steady, producing 1,000 cases by 1970. Fortunes changed in 1972 when California native Richard Nixon carried 25 cases to China to celebrate the return of diplomatic relations there. An act that has made Schramsberg a mainstay in the White House cellar to this day. The next California president, Ronald Reagan, was known to serve it to congressional easterners and jokingly challenge them to find a better wine in France. The Davies’ success story of making quality sparkling wine in California eventually got out to Europe which sparked a buying spree of Carneros land by famous French cellars like Tattinger, Moet &amp;amp; Chandon, Mumm, and Spanish Cava producer Cordoníu. The Davies were not the first to make sparkling wine in California…they just set the standard. They were also active in other fronts regarding Napa Valley. Here are some of their accomplishments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to plant Champagne varietals/clones in Napa.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to produce sparkling wine in California using Champagne’s traditional method.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to produce vintage Blanc de Noirs (1967)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leaders in the movement to declare Napa Valley an agricultural perserve.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Successfully helped stop the widening of highway 29 from 2-to-4 lanes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schramsberg has been served at White House events by every President since 1972.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Robert-Mondavi-10004083.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Robert Mondavi&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Robert Mondavi. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbrands.com/&quot;&gt;– © Constellation Brands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;robert-mondavi&quot;&gt;Robert Mondavi&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 7 mentioned here, none are arguably more famous than Robert Mondavi…and Robert wouldn’t have it any other way. Mondavi was an excellent winemaker in his own right, but his real skills and contribution to the wine industry were in marketing. While everyone else was in the pursuit of creating high quality wine, Robert was obsessed with how sell it to the masses. Even though Robert’s contributions to the wine industry really didn’t erupt until the 1970s I include him in this list because it was his early marketing vision in the 1960s that helped future wineries find consumers beyond their tasting rooms. Mondavi is the father of a vision that fine wine should be a part of everyday American life. Elevating people to aspire beyond the jug. To say Robert was restless would be an understatement. Born in Lodi, CA Robert and his brother Peter helped their grape-growing father Cesare start a new venture after buying Charles Krug Winery in St. Helena. By 1946 CK Mondavi had established a reputation for producing affordable everyday wines. However, after their father’s death in 1959 the brothers grew contentious. While Peter believed in his father’s vision Robert had higher aspirations. By 1965 their infamous feud had exploded with Robert leaving the winery in a controversial manor to start his own Robert Mondavi Winery. Robert immediately started spending and borrowing to fund his ambitions. A practice that kept him in debt the rest of his life. However, no expenses were spared. Robert always purchased the best equipment and his modern winery and tasting room built in 1966 began an opulent Vegas-like building boom that continues today. The same attention was spent on his wine in consulting Andre Tchelistcheff and ultimately hiring Mike Grgich. However, Robert’s ambitions would eventually get the best of him resulting in an embarrassing sale of his winery and name to Constellation Brands. even still, his legacy is revered and his accomplishments are many. Here are but a few:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revived the unpopular Sauvignon Blanc by aging it in oak and selling it under the name “Fumé Blanc.” A practice so successful many other winemakers across the state followed suit and the made up nomer continues to this day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stopped the decline of the maligned Zinfandel by introducing it to French oak and selling on par with the more popular Cabernet Sauvignon. Although, Napa vintners continued to replace their Zin with Cab, Sonoma vintners followed Robert’s example and kept Zin as their cult favorite.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By establishing his Woodbridge brand with a large production facility in Lodi, Mondavi brought 750ml premium Napa wine to the masses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Partnered with Baron Philippe de Rothschild of Chateau Mouton Rothschild fame to found Opus One–which quickly became one of the Napa’s first cult Cabernets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contributed millions of dollars to UC Davis’ enology and viticulture programs helping feed the growing demand for educated winemaking and vineyard staff throughout the US.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Martin-Ray-pours-wine-namesake-Saratoga-winery.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Martin Ray&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Martin Ray&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;martin-ray&quot;&gt;Martin Ray&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a series about Napa vs. Sonoma. This post is about early pioneers of the modern wine era. The first 6 mentioned operated in Napa Valley. This, the 7th and final, did not. Nor did he in Sonoma. Martin Ray hails from the region I first discovered wine and still hold very dear–the Santa Cruz Mountains. Martin Ray makes this list because way back in 1936, even before Lee Stewart, he was an outspoken advocate of single varietal wines and varietal labeling. At a time when bulk wine producers were producing wines like California Chablis and Hearty Burgundy (neither of which had much, if any, of their French namesake grapes), Ray was adamant that wines should be 100% varietal and labeled as such. Surprising, since his mentor was none other than Paul Masson, a very successful bulk producer who ironically sold his vineyards to Ray. Eventually Ray’s vision caught on. Not just in the Santa Cruz Mountains, but all over California. Bombastic, boastful, eccentric, and perhaps a bit crazy, Ray was famous for lavish parties and outlandish statements. His wine was adored by critics, but expensive and hard to get. Ray’s antics eventually got him forced out of the business by his financial partners in 1972, but his vision on how wine should be produced and labeled actually became law in 1982. Although I have no professional accolades for Martin Ray, I shiver at the prospect of rows of bottles being labeled “California Red Wine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I chose 7 individuals who were pivotal in California’s movement to produce quality wine beyond the then current “jug” standard. Admittedly, my selection is subjective. Howerver, one thing is fairly obvious…6 out of 7 operated in Napa Valley. Oh, Sonoma was producing quality wine in the early days, but relatively quietly. In fact, heavily funded Hanzell Winery near downtown Sonoma had become a virtual experimentation lab frequented by many of the pioneers mentioned in this post. Still, there weren’t the personalities, collaboration, and vision that was going on in Napa at the time. The Delingers, DeLoach’s, Bynums, Strongs, Stares, would all come later. But at the end of the 1960’s, thanks to winemakers like the my magnificent 7, the modern wine era had emerged. In my next post we will find out how a Federal farm bill, an ambitious winemaker, and an investment-seeking bank touched off a wave of new California vintners known as the Class of ‘72.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 05:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/tale-of-two-counties-p8/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/tale-of-two-counties-p8/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yno Tasting Beta Program.</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;yno-tasting-as-a-winery-event&quot;&gt;Yno Tasting as a Winery Event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yno concept evolved from the most asked question I received during my time in hospitality, “How do I find wines I like?” It made me think about my own wine journey and how important blind tasting wine in a comparative setting has helped me discover my own palate as well as enjoyment of wine. However, blind tastings should have rules and structure if there is going to be any benefit–a perfect challenge for an old wine guy with a programming problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yno Tasting is intended to be as much a consumer app as an industry event. The idea is for wine enthusiasts to set up Yno Tasting accounts in order to participate in public events hosted by wineries, wine bars, or even virtually by wine experts. With that experience they should be encouraged to host their own private events. Yno Tasters and Hosts will have an ongoing record of their tastings, ratings, and comments. Meanwhile the accumulation of all Yno Tasting events will provide valuable comparative data to the industry as a whole. It’s a win-win for both industry and consumer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;yno-tasting-beta-program&quot;&gt;Yno Tasting Beta Program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all has to start some where. That is why I am introducing a beta program to help kickstart winery events. I believe once winery customers recognize how much fun blind tastings are, they will host their own tastings, wineries will get increased loyalty, cats and dogs living together, the possibilities are endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-host-a-public-yno-tasting-event&quot;&gt;How to Host a Public Yno Tasting Event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public events are conducted as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up a Yno Tasting Host account on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ynotasting.com&quot;&gt;https://ynotasting.com&lt;/a&gt;. It is preferable to use the wine maker or owner’s name on the account to bring credibility to the event regardless of who actually hosts it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up a Yno Tasting Event. Name the event appropriately with your establishment name as well as other pertinent info like new releases, library, vertical, etc… It is up to the host whether to reveal the wines being tasted, or keep it a surprise until tasting time. Keep in mind this is not intended to be a competition as much it is a discovery. For responsible hospitality reasons it is recommended to keep your list to just 6 wines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yno Tasting Invitations. It is recommended to use your normal event system to invite your guests, accept payment, etc… After a guest confirms attendance, use the Yno Tasting invite system to send them a confirmation and link to signing up as Yno Tasting Guest for your event. Yno Tasting Guest confirmations will be sent to the host’s email account. Non-confirmed guests can still sign up on arrival.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tasting Day!
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;IMPORTANT! Your guests will need to bring their cell phones and your facility will need reliable cell or wifi coverage in order to conduct the event. See beta hosting information below about using Amazon Alexa devices.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Until all wines are revealed, they are referred to by number. Use numbered bottles/carafes of the same shape and size. Best practice is to provide one glass per bottle with matching number for each guest. This will speed things along and require less pouring staff than using one glass per Guest.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Expect the event to last about 1.5 hours for 6 wines. This should allow enough time for wine introductions and tasting instructions. It is recommended to set a “close” date/time for your event which will trigger a hard stop and block any further entry. At this point the host can reveal the wines via the app and the event is over.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post event data. All tasting data will remain available for review for each event under the Host’s account as well as to their Guests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beta-host&quot;&gt;Beta Host.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yno Tasting is currently in beta. During this period I strongly recommend using me as your host for at least your first tasting. This is to make sure everything goes smoothly and for me to observe what works and what needs improvement. I have over 3 years of experience in hospitality at &lt;a href=&quot;https://chateaustjean.com&quot;&gt;Chateau St. Jean&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://drycreekvineyard.com&quot;&gt;Dry Creek Vineyard&lt;/a&gt; where I’ve conducted many hospitality events such as tours, tastings and blendings. I come with CSW and WSET III wine education certificates and references. In addition, I will bring Alexa devices which offer another fun dimension to your event. For the beta period I am charging a modest $50 fee to manage and host your event. Please keep in mind that I do have a day job at &lt;a href=&quot;https://wineglassmarketing.com&quot;&gt;WineGlass Marketing&lt;/a&gt; (which by-the-way is available to help promote your event) that limits my availability to nights and weekends. Should your event be a success–which I’m certain it will–you are welcome to host future events with your own staff. Currently, there is no cost to use the platform, however that is subject to change in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested parties can reach me at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Langley&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:bill@ynoguy.com&quot;&gt;bill@ynoguy.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(o) 707-237-6904&lt;br /&gt;
(m) 408-314-4304&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 09:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/yno-tasting-event-beta-hosting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/yno-tasting-event-beta-hosting/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What the Hell is a Wine Club? Final Post.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my final post on my wine club series. In my &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p1/&quot;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt; I illustrated the difference between retail and DTC clubs. In &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p2/&quot;&gt;post 2&lt;/a&gt; I illustrated the genesis of why wine clubs even exist. In this post I will hypothesize the future of wine clubs in the rapidly changing world of hand-crafted adult beverages and end this series with my 7 tips on choosing a wine club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;craft-beer-is-here&quot;&gt;Craft Beer is Here!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/maxresdefault.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Santa Rosa Brews&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where wine country meets beer city&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve mentioned before I live in Sonoma County. A county once best known as a premium wine producer. That was until 2 years ago when my home town of Santa Rosa was named &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sonomamag.com/santa-rosa-named-microbrew-capital-united-states/&quot;&gt;Microbrew Capital of the US&lt;/a&gt;.  My wife and I own a home downtown within a mile of the famed &lt;a href=&quot;https://russianriverbrewing.com&quot;&gt;Russian River Brewing&lt;/a&gt; Co. We have an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/21461228&quot;&gt;Airbnb&lt;/a&gt; which is often booked up 20+ days a month. You would think that is because I offer wine tours and advice to my guests, but you would be wrong. Nearly half of our guests are beer tourists and most are a blend of beer and wine, as well as cider and spirits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Craft brewing has swept the nation. I visit Bend, OR every year where brew pubs outnumber coffee shops. In my birth town of Milwaukee, WI, once dominated by Miller Brewing, craft breweries are popping up everywhere. In fact, it is arguably hard to find a town in the US that doesn’t have one. People are excited to try each new limited release and pay upwards of $10/pint! Stand outside RRBC at 11a on Sunday morning you will see scores of beer tourists and locals walking out with their case of Pliny the Elder. Come back in February and you’ll see them lined up around the block for week to get their 2 pints of Pliny the Younger. It’s a phenomenon that has swept the nation. People have come to realize that small batch beer…well, tastes better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dt.common.streams.StreamServer.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Line at RRBC&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Published by the Press Democrat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-good-for-beer-is-good-for-wine-right&quot;&gt;What’s Good for Beer is Good for Wine, Right?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I discuss in my &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/tale-of-two-counties-p1/&quot;&gt;Tale of Two Counties series&lt;/a&gt;, quality small batch wine has been around here in California since before the 1960s. One would think recent rise in trends like craft breweries and farm-to-table food can only benefit the wine industry. Well, not quite. There is one glaring advantage why small batch beer, cider, spirits, and even food, have over wine…they can be made ANYWHERE. As I’ve said 1,000 times quality wine comes from vineyards and quality vineyards can’t thrive just anywhere. Plus, the faster you can get those grapes from vine to fermentation, the better your chances of a quality product. The same is not true of grains, hops, or apples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pubs-not-clubs&quot;&gt;Pubs Not Clubs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A beer made in Lincoln, Nebraska has the same potential quality as a beer made here in Santa Rosa. For that reason, microbrews focus solely their local market where they can depend on local brew pubs and restaurants for distribution. As breweries increase they are facing the same limited distribution issue as wine. The days of starting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://https://lagunitas.com&quot;&gt;Lagunitas Brewing Company&lt;/a&gt; story are fast closing, so new establishments don’t even try. Stay small, local, and thrive is the new model. Subsequently, new wineries are adopting the same model–which is great…if you live here. Not so much if you live in Lincoln. Although I’ve never been there, I’m reasonable certain I could find a good local brew. However, I am also certain I could not find a local wine of the same caliber as I can here in Santa Rosa. Sure, I would likely find a good quality small batch wine from CA, OR, WA, etc… in a local shop or restaurant, but as I discussed in my &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p2/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; over time that is likely to change. The wine industry is rapidly bifurcating into local small batch vs. mass produced distribution–with very little in between. It’s the same for beer, but with less consequences depending on where you live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-the-club-alive&quot;&gt;Keep the Club Alive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why winery wine clubs are so important. Unfortunately, many of wineries have turned their clubs into overly aggressive sales programs. For some wineries it’s out of greed, for others it’s a desperate act of survival. Don’t get me wrong, even the best wineries have to be clever in the face of competition, but there is a point of diminishing returns. As a club salesman, I have witnessed it first hand. Today I work as a software developer in wine marketing where I hope to help evolve the club system into something more friendly and accessible to consumers. My wish is some day we can eliminate the need for aggressive tasting room sales tactics. I believe if we don’t throttle this, eventually clubs will turn consumers away from wine rather than towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now I can at least recommend to wine lovers my 7 tips on how to pick a good wine club:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beware of the conglomerates:&lt;/strong&gt; I want to be clear not to steer you away from conglomerate owned wineries. There are honest business models out there where subsidiaries are producing quality small batch wines. Many allow you to enjoy your discounts at their sister wineries, which is a big benefit. Simply do your research before signing up. For instance, when the salesman tells you, “You can’t find this in any stores,” casually pull out your phone and look it up. It’s not that they’re lying to you, just more likely they don’t know what happens in the boardroom. Another easy trick is look for a barcode sku on the label. All distributed wines require one, while DTC wines do not. Never join a club where any of the wines may be distributed. You’re better off joining a club at your local wine shop.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s their story?&lt;/strong&gt; The genesis of a winery tells a lot about what goes into making the product. There are lots of very small wineries with stories like, “John Doe made a ton of money as a hedge fund investor. He learned a lot about wine on his (multiple) trips to France. So, 3 years ago he and his wife thought, ‘Why not?’ and here we are. His wife now runs the winery. This bottle is named after his daughter.” At this point, I usually like to ask questions like, “Is his wife on the property right now?” “Do they make the wine?” “Do they live here full time?” I think you know what the answers are. These are what we call “lifestyle” vintners. To them, winemaking is a tax-deductible hobby…not a passion. Steer clear.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vineyard relationships:&lt;/strong&gt; Good wine starts with great vineyards. Great vineyards are hard to find and even harder to maintain. Wineries that establish long-term contracts with vineyards usually produce quality wines from them year-over-year. This is important if you plan to be a long-term member. Wineries that own vineyards are even better, because they have full control and generally have more cash to put towards winemaking. If a winery commonly produces wine from different vineyards every year, unless the winemaker really knows his craft, there is a likelihood consistency will suffer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ecology matters:&lt;/strong&gt; Wine is an agricultural product. It is essentially farming. Anyone who takes it seriously cares about the land and community it comes from. Vineyard sustainability, dry farming, climate change, watershed preservation, local wild life, community and farm worker support are all topics of conversation you should be hearing and having at the winery. Bad behavior is well documented. Know who the good guys are.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy wine, not trophies:&lt;/strong&gt; Wines costing over $100/bottle are basically like printing money. Despite all the accolades you might hear about them, there is nothing in the vineyard or cellar that can justify that price other than demand–and demand is usually driven by hype, not quality. Unless you are looking to impress the likes of Robert Parker with your wine cellar, focus on wines you can taste, afford, and enjoy every day. Besides, nobody likes a snob.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be wary of scarcity:&lt;/strong&gt; Small batch wines are by nature limited in quantity. However, there are wineries that take advantage of scarcity as a business model. There are famous examples called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/articles/collectors-clamor-for-napas-cult-wines-51544882400&quot;&gt;cult wines&lt;/a&gt;, which are almost impossible to come by and often run in excess of $500/bottle. This can be an expensive and frustrating game to play where wines are often doled out in what’s called “allocation”. For every day wine drinkers the experience can sometimes feel indignant and humiliating. There are good allocation models where access is guaranteed with some benefits, but I consider these programs different than a traditional wine club. They are strictly about the wine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Membership should have privileges:&lt;/strong&gt; Most wine clubs come with benefits. Discounts should be at the top of the list, but many offer free or discounted events, tours, winemaker dinners, merchandise, etc.. For those of us who love the winery “experience” as much as the wine, these perks are important. As a member you are virtually a stock holder in their business. A good winery should always make you feel like a VIP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it! Hopefully, now you know what the hell a wine club is and whether it’s something you want to get into to. Feel free to reach out to me with questions and comments on this often controversial topic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 05:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-final/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-final/</guid>
        
        <category>wineclub</category>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yno Tasting</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;another-left-turn&quot;&gt;Another left turn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I announced some &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/up-dry-creek-with-a-pin/&quot;&gt;pretty big career changes&lt;/a&gt;. Back then I was starting my first full-time job in the wine industry and had aspirations of being a “high-end” wine educator and blogger. My software developer days were forever behind me–or so I thought. After about a year I started feeling uncomfortable in my role as an “educator.” I started getting imposter syndrome and, more importantly, I didn’t feel like I was  helping people discover wine for themselves. After all, I wanted to be an educator, not an expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also, as a software developer, finding myself increasingly frustrated with the sales and marketing software I was using in my job. So, after two years at Dry Creek Vineyard—an experience that I will always cherish—I decided to take a job with a small direct-to-consumer marketing company called &lt;a href=&quot;https://wineglassmarketing.com&quot;&gt;WineGlass Marketing&lt;/a&gt; as a data analyst and programmer. At the same time I enrolled in a software bootcamp to retool my development skills and while there decided to develop a software app idea I had been toying with for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Have you ever asked yourself why Sommeliers and Wine Masters have to take those arduous blind tasting tests? Sure, they have to show they can recognize what’s in the glass, but it’s also the best way to actually learn. Students do blind tastings to get good at them, but they also learn the different nuances of varietals, styles and regions along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love tasting wine blind—even though I’m not particularly good at it. I especially like to do it with friends. If you ever want to make a wine snob cringe, invite them to a blind tasting. It’s a lot of fun, but more importantly, it’s flat out the best way to discover wines you like with no flowery descriptions, no pretty labels, and no point scores. It’s just you and your senses comparing 6 wines. You either like it, or you don’t…and isn’t that all that matters?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-yno&quot;&gt;Let’s Yno!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ynotasting.com&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/yno_tasting_logo_512.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yno Tasting&quot; class=&quot;portfolio-hero-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own blind tasting experiences my friends and I always struggled with doing the tally at the end of the tasting. Sure, we all knew what we liked, but what did everyone like? What was the best buy? This required math. Something nobody should have to deal with after a night of tasting wine. So, for many years the idea of a blind wine tasting app has been kicking around in my head. Done right, the app would have to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a hosted invite system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Display tasting and wine descriptions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep track of taster scores and comments by wine number&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep a running tab on overall tasting statistics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close a tasting and reveal the wines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage interaction between tasters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Store tasting data for tasters to review later&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be fun and easy to use (this one especially)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing &lt;a href=&quot;https://ynotasting.com&quot;&gt;Yno Tasting&lt;/a&gt;. This app will hopefully accomplish what I originally set out to do as a wine educator: help people enjoy wine more by learning what they like. The app is free for all to use. Just sign up as a &lt;em&gt;Yno Host&lt;/em&gt; and start your own tasting. I will provide affordable suggested tasting lists of commonly found wines for those needing a kickstart. Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:bill@ynoguy.com&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; with your questions/suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now get out there, and &lt;em&gt;Go Blind!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 02:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/yno-tasting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/yno-tasting/</guid>
        
        <category>wine software</category>
        
        
        <category>Software</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What the Hell is a Wine Club? Part 2.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p1/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I tried to explain the definition of a wine club, and the difference between a retail wine club and a winery wine club. In this post I will try to explain the evolution of the wine club and why they exist in the first place. The fact of the matter is wine clubs are now basically loyalty programs, but that’s not how they started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-very-brief-history-of-alcohol-in-america&quot;&gt;A (Very) Brief History of Alcohol in America&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s 1933 and America’s great experiment, Prohibition, is failing miserably. Americans now disapprove of the 19th Amendment by an overwhelming majority. Organized crime has become more brazen and incredibly wealthy distributing illegal hooch from Canada, Europe, and the Caribbean. Moonshiners are showing off their get-away cars in a new sport called “stock car” racing. Citizens are poisoning themselves with “bath tub” gin and wineries are selling unusually high amounts of “sacramental” wine. The federal government has had enough. However, Prohibition was a part of the Constitution and, as we currently know with the ACA, turning it back won’t be easy. It will require another Amendment and many states are still quite satisfied with the status quo. Compromise will be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reticent states insisted they should be able to control the flow of alcohol across their borders. Legally, interstate trade is protected under the Constitution–but these were desperate times. The solution came to be known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parkstreet.com/wine-spirits-industry-background/&quot;&gt;3 Tier system&lt;/a&gt;. It declared that alcohol production, distribution, and retail were to be separated entities giving states full control over distribution. Retailers would not be allowed to purchase alcohol directly from a producer, making each state’s distributor a gatekeeper. It was a strange “tail wagging the dog” compromise that was hastily drafted for ratification, albeit wrought with loopholes and constitutional hypocrisy. Some states like Utah and Ohio chose to handle distribution as a government function. Other states restricted distributor licenses to just a handful. Subsequently, 80 years later the system &lt;a href=&quot;https://fermentationwineblog.com/2018/09/a-corrupt-scheme-at-the-middle-of-the-american-wine-industry/&quot;&gt;looks nothing like what was intended&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://winefolly.com/update/three-tier-system/&quot;&gt;is straining in the face of corporate deregulation and the internet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-very-brief-history-of-wine-distribution-in-america&quot;&gt;A (Very) Brief History of Wine Distribution in America&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the end of Prohibition wine was largely made in bulk by brands like Gallo, Inglenook, and Almaden. With so few producers making relatively few large volume labels, it was easy for distributors to carry virtually every wine made. However, as early as the 1950’s small wineries in California like Robert Mondavi, Louis Martini, Beaulieu Vineyards, and others were producing small batch wines. Most of the country didn’t take notice until the famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judgment_of_Paris_(wine)&quot;&gt;Paris Tasting of 1976&lt;/a&gt; when California Cabernet and Chardonnay suddenly achieved world acclaim. Small wine producers started popping up everywhere–particularly in California, which to date has over 1,500 wine producers. On the other hand, while the number of wine producers was exploding, the number of state distributors were doing the exact opposite. One of the loopholes of the 3 Tier system permits distributors to operate in multiple states, thus enabling mergers and acquisitions. A once small Florida distributor called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/companies/southern-wine-spirits/#7787f1415a59&quot;&gt;Southern Wine &amp;amp; Spirits&lt;/a&gt; now controls the flow of alcohol in over 35 states. The result: thousands of wineries trying to get a relative handful of distributors to carry their products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/free-the-grapes-angry-grape-guy.png&quot; alt=&quot;freethegrapes.org&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Free the Grapes! (freethegrapes.org)! An organization dedicated to direct-to-consumer shipping causes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-dtc-shipping&quot;&gt;Introducing DTC Shipping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we have here is a failure to distribute which, when you think about it, is just another form of prohibition. And like in Prohibition, consumers and wine producers often became partners in crime. With a nod-and-wink wine would be shipped marked as “olive oil” or some other non-restricted product. Punishment for such crimes–especially for the winery-could be severe, including loss of their wholesale license. Effectively banning the sale of their wine to the entire state! However, wine producing states started to realize it was unreasonable and just bad business to not allow their own small wine producers the ability to sell direct-to-consumer (DTC) when the consumer had no other means to purchase the product. “Reciprocity” deals, as they were called, were drawn up between states that allowed the free flow of wine between producers and consumers of limited quantities. Eventually, other states started opening up some form of direct shipping as well. Even though wholesalers and distributors effectively sought legislation to strike down reciprocity, the proverbial cat is now out of the bag and over 40 states now allow some form of DTC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-inevitable-collision&quot;&gt;The Inevitable Collision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say the least, wholesalers and distributors don’t like direct sales. They view it as a loophole to what is their constitutional domain. They have fought it tooth-and-nail over the years through lobbyists, law suits, and political contributions. However, consumer demand, producer frustration, and the enforcement of interstate trade laws have been slowly chipping away at their stronghold. Given their situation you would think they’d try to be more accommodating to small producers. In fact, again, they are doing just the opposite. They are shunning them in favor of working more exclusively with wine conglomerates. Why? Well, they actually have mutually exclusive motivations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For conglomerates, forcing small producers to sell out increases their own portfolio. Having more brands gives them leverage over distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For distributors, dealing exclusively with conglomerates enables them to access larger portfolios with less leg work and more bargains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a win-win…except for consumers and retailers. In many instances, wine shops and restaurants are forced into purchasing big brand wine since most of them are at the mercy of what the distributor carries. Meanwhile in stores wine aisles are looking more like cereal aisles. Lots of pretty labels…from just a handful of corporations. So the battle rages on, but inch-by-inch DTC is gaining ground. Since I entered the wine biz 5 years ago formerly stalwart distribution states like Pennsylvania, Massachusetts, and now Oklahoma have opened up. Fundamentally, 3-Tier violates interstate trade commerce law and everyone knows it is just one Supreme Court decision away from being overturned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dtc--wine-club&quot;&gt;DTC = Wine Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh yeah, back to wine clubs. Small batch wines are the least likely to be distributed for obvious reasons. They are also often the most highly rated available. Consumers clamor for these wines, but buying them takes timing. Many of these wines disappear weeks, or even days, after they’re released. Oh sure, you can get on an email list, but wouldn’t it just be better if you can have your favorite new releases automatically shipped to your door when they come out..guaranteed? This is why, as I alluded in the beginning of this series, I favor winery wine clubs over others. Retail clubs have to rely more on gimmicks to compete. I find some of their claims to be rather dubious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We search for hard-to-get wines.&lt;/strong&gt; As I said before, if they’re not coming directly from a winery, they are sold on the open market. Look it up in your &lt;a href=&quot;https://delectable.com&quot;&gt;Delectable&lt;/a&gt; app…you’ll probably find it. Besides, just because it’s hard to find doesn’t mean you’ll like it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our panel will select wines especially for you.&lt;/strong&gt; Really?! An “expert” selects wine for someone they don’t really know. This is literally the blind leading the blind. Why not just go to your local wine shop and ask them for advice? At least you can actually meet the expert.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’ll select wines based on your sample ratings.&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe you’ve seen this. They send you some sample vials of wine. You tell them which ones you liked and…Voila! Every wine after will be perfect. Like most, the first wine I ever tasted and liked was sweet and cheap. My taste has changed quite a bit since then…and continues to do so. Listen, if you really want to track what you like use my software &lt;a href=&quot;https://ynotasting.com&quot;&gt;YnoTasting&lt;/a&gt;. After all, it’s your palate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many retail clubs offer great wines and values, but the fact is only a winery wine club offers small batch, hand crafted wines that can’t be found any other way. In the end, wine clubs aren’t for everybody. They’re expensive and shipping can be a pain. However, increasingly wine clubs and DTC sales are the only champions of consumer choice in the wine industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my final post on this subject I will discuss why small batch wines matter and how the craft beer boom may actually save the wine industry…if it doesn’t kill it first.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 02:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p2/</guid>
        
        <category>wineclub</category>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yno Wine Trivia</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/yno_trivia_logo_512.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yno Wine Trivia&quot; class=&quot;portfolio-hero-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What “non-existent” wine did Ellen Barkin offer Matt Damon in &lt;em&gt;Oceans 13&lt;/em&gt;? Where does &lt;em&gt;Gruner Veltliner&lt;/em&gt; come from? These questions and more are answered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Brainstorm-Creative-Wine-Trivia/dp/B071Y1HRP1/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-skills&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1503377224&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=wine+trivia&quot;&gt;Yno Wine Trivia&lt;/a&gt;. A fun Alexa skill to play with friends or study for WSET, Sommelier, or CSW tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;curiosity-and-study&quot;&gt;Curiosity and Study&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How do I learn more about wine?” As a wine educator I’ve encountered this question more times than I can remember. The problem is wine is a daunting subject. I often refer to it as the world‘s 2nd oldest profession. It‘s history, viticulture, and production go back centuries. So, where does one start to get a taste of what it‘s like to learn about wine?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From my own journey with wine I’ve found that large part of it’s enjoyment starts with education&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alexa-fied&quot;&gt;Alexa-fied&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voice-enabled digital assistants are fast becoming the next consumer must-have. Amazon’s Alexa is an industry leader. The simple act of asking a question without reaching for a mobile device or tapping a keyboard breaks down barriers for software developers. In addition, Alexa’s built-in trivia skill makes it even easier. I could not build an app like Yno Wine Trivia as fun and compelling without Alexa. Nor could I build it as fast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 01:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/yno-trivia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/yno-trivia/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Software</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What the Hell is a Wine Club? Part 1.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post series I want to address what I think is a very misunderstood concept–Wine Clubs. My thoughts on this were confirmed by an article I read some time ago from Wall Street Journal’s wine columnist Lettie Teague called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/do-wine-clubs-really-deliver-on-their-promises-1422646193&quot;&gt;Do Wine Clubs Really Deliver on Their Promises?&lt;/a&gt; Now to be clear, I’m not questioning Ms. Teague’s credentials as a columnist, but with regards to this topic I think she’s missing the point. In her article she joins three clubs, none of which are direct from wineries. There is a key distinction here. All of the wines she was receiving were delivered through distribution, meaning even though she may never have heard of them, these wines are available to the public through one means or another. This is a very different kind of club vs. what most wineries offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, explaining what wine clubs are, their differences, why they exist, and what the benefits are for consumers and sellers alike will take more than a single post. The answers are complicated and the genesis for their existence dates back to the end of prohibition. So, I’ll begin by illustrating what a wine club is and its history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-is-a-wine-club&quot;&gt;So, What is a Wine Club?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In brief, a wine club is a loyalty program. It usually consists of a commitment to purchase a  quantity of wine over a period of time at pre-determined intervals. Commitments are usually defined as shipments. The amount of wine per shipment can vary from a couple bottles to 12 or more. After the minimum commitment is met (usually a year’s worth of shipments) you can choose to cancel or allow it to continue indefinitely. In most clubs, the seller chooses the wines, but some are now allowing the consumer to choose from a list. Once you choose a club, wines are shipped direct to your home or business and you are billed per shipment. There is usually a minimum commitment of year, after which you can cancel anytime. Simple, no? No, definitely not. Wine clubs were traditionally sold by wineries, but are now being sold through wine shops, online retailers, and yes, even the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsjwine.com/&quot;&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;winery-wine-clubs&quot;&gt;Winery Wine Clubs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wineries were the first to sell wine clubs. In fact, until 2004 wineries were the only entities that could sell wine direct-to-consumers (aka DTC). It is generally accepted the first wine club was actually the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ridgewine.com/atp40/&quot;&gt;Automatic Tasting Program (ATP)&lt;/a&gt; introduced by Ridge Winery in 1977.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ATP40Logo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ridge Vineyards ATP&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ridge Winery’s “Automatic Tasting Program” is considered by most the first wine club.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a teenager growing up near their winery in Saratoga, CA when my dad joined the program. Back then it wasn’t a “shipping” as much a “sampling” program where local customers would journey to the winery to get their new releases to take home, try and enjoy. The winery would then offer the same wines at a discount so that members could immediately purchase their favorites. My dad and his buddies eagerly awaited each release to the point where the “journey” to Ridge became more a celebrated pilgrimage. Their excitement was around the differences each vineyard, varietal, and vintage would bring. This excitement is why many people join winery wine clubs to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it took years before wineries could actually ship club wines to consumers in other states. The vagaries of the 21st amendment and dreaded 3-Tier System have slowed progress in DTC sales. I will discuss more on this in a later chapter. Today, virtually every winery has some form of DTC program. One of my favorite local wineries (&lt;a href=&quot;http://drycreekvineyard.com&quot;&gt;Dry Creek Vineyard&lt;/a&gt;) has a club program with options ranging from $250-$650 per year. Incentives include 20-25% off wine as well as discount shipping and special events/perks at the winery itself like free tours and tastings. As I alluded earlier, what’s important to note about winery clubs is they concentrate on selling wines DTC they don’t sell via distribution. The consumer is getting access to unique, small production wines they can not get any other way. Sometimes this is confused as a “holding back” tactic on the winery’s part to drive up price and exclusivity. I will discuss why this isn’t true in a later post as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;retail-and-internet-wine-clubs&quot;&gt;Retail and Internet Wine Clubs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom:1rem&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;background-color:#000; padding: 1rem; text-align:center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://tastingroom.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/logo_clean.png&quot; width=&quot;200px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75rem; margin-top:.5rem&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tasting Room Wine Club&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004 the Supreme Court forbid wine export states from disallowing wine imported from other states. This opened the door for not only more wineries to sell across state lines, but retailers as well–especially over the internet. Online wine retailers, clubs, and “flash” sites have been popping up ever since. Wineries themselves opened their own DTC websites. Overall, it has been a positive development for the wine industry. However, unlike winery clubs, the retail club value proposition is very different. Club W, now called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tastingroom.com&quot;&gt;Tasting Room&lt;/a&gt; and mentioned in Ms. Teague’s article, feels a bit more like a dating site than a wine retailer. Club managers are purchasing wine available on the open market from wholesalers they perceive as offering wines that are unique, of good value, and match their customers tastes. That’s a far cry from what a winery club offers. With some exceptions there are a lot of middlemen taking a cut of these wines; importers, distributors, wholesalers, even other retailers. Retail clubs are a great way to discover wine as whole. However, because they are selling wines that are available on the open market, they tend to lean on marketing gimmicks like tailoring wine to your palette (which, by the way is constantly changing), price target, expert choice, etc.. I appreciate what they’re doing, but I don’t think it’s anything like a winery club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-sell-wine-this-way&quot;&gt;Why Sell Wine this Way?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the deal? Why not just sell all wine in stores or over the internet like everything else? I’m both a wine club salesman and member. I’ll be the first to say it’s a wacky way to sell wine. On the surface it can even seem disingenuous. Despite this, DTC sales are increasing much faster than retail. Most industry experts still dismiss DTC as a minor part of the market (&amp;lt;5% overall), but for smaller wineries it is an essential–if not only part of their sales strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how can a subscription based service that requires the consumer to;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commit to an annual minimum purchase&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be home to sign for delivery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and, not even be sure of what they’re getting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;be so successful? As they say, the Devil is in the details. In this case, I’m afraid there are more Devils than details. In my next post I’ll discuss why the compromise to end Prohibition has a lot to do with how wine clubs came to be, and why they are becoming more popular so many years later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2015 01:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2015/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2015/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p1/</guid>
        
        <category>wineclub</category>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adiós Penedès.</title>
        <description>&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/20140904_183438_HDR.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View over St. Pau&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;View over St. Pau&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been over a month since I returned from Spain, but I thought it important to share some insights on my visit to Penedès. Wine tourism is not always easy. There are obvious language barriers, but perhaps more importantly, different customs in different regions regarding wine tasting and tours. I went largely unprepared and encountered some stumbles because of it. Here are my recommendations for visiting Penedès.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;habla-español&quot;&gt;Habla Español…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or better yet, learn some Catalan. We stayed in a lovely little village where no one spoke English. The simplest tasks were difficult. Barcelona (about 40 mins away) is a bustling, beautiful, international city where, as a result of its tourism industry, has a lot more English speaking citizens. If you can’t speak a lick of Spanish, stay here. You’re life will be much easier. Make day trips into wine country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/20140831_141555_HDR.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Catalan Fiesta celebration&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Catalan Fiesta celebration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;know-your-spanishcatalan-holidays&quot;&gt;Know your Spanish/Catalan Holidays&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you live in a small town in the U.S. you might be used to stores closing for a week or more when their owners go on vacation…if you live in a very small town. I can tell you from experience this custom is alive and well in Spain. We visited Catalonia at possibly the worst time. Our Labor Day is Catalonian Fiesta Day, while 9/11 is Catalonian Independence Day. During this two-week period it is not uncommon for store and restaurant owners to close for the duration. All three restaurants in our little town of Sant Pau d’Ordal were closed for nearly the entire duration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adopt-the-siesta-life&quot;&gt;Adopt the Siesta Life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to visiting Spain I, of course, knew about siesta. The French and English have similar customs of closing during lunch time. However, the Spanish take this concept to a whole new level. Siesta starts somewhere between noon and 1pm. No problem here. However, I never did quite understand when it ended. Stores have posted hours of operation like we do here, but unlike us these are more-or-less intended as “guidelines” vs. rules. Also, unlike France and the U.K., in Spain EVERYONE goes on siesta. Not just stores, but bakeries, charcuteries, national parks, museums, and even tourism offices. From the hours of 1p to 3p-ish, towns appear to be literally abandoned. Larger cities like Barcelona are an exception, but in the small towns siesta is serious, um, non-business. As a tourist you need to plan accordingly. Even though you’re on vacation, get up early enough to see sights and tours. This is really the only time of day you can be somewhat spontaneous. During siesta, there are some tapas bars open to at least get lunch, but afternoon events can be dicey if unbooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;youre-not-in-california-anymore&quot;&gt;You’re Not in California Anymore&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wine tourists are pretty spoiled throughout California. They can find an abundance of wineries open nearly everyday including Holidays. The more adventurous know that most smaller wineries are by appointment only. Throughout Europe, appointments are the rule with virtually all wineries. The problem is most family-owned wineries are unknown to us Americans, so how does one find them. I didn’t do enough research before I went, but I got lucky when I visited &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/greetings-from-penedes-day-3/&quot;&gt;Albet i Noya&lt;/a&gt;. My host Marta was gracious enough to give me a list of wineries to visit–which is how I learned about &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/greetings-from-penedes-day-6/&quot;&gt;Can Rà fols dels Caus&lt;/a&gt;. Another method is to find a wine bar and inquire there…which I did at the &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/greetings-from-penedes-day-5/&quot;&gt;Vinseum in Vila Franca&lt;/a&gt;. In any case, plan ahead as much as possible and try and keep your schedule open to appointment availability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-the-path-less-traveled&quot;&gt;Take the Path Less Traveled!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are easier ways to travel to foreign countries. Most Americans take the path most traveled. They stay at brand name hotels, go on English-speaking tours, eat at English-friendly restaurants and ultimately, see and do all the same things every other tourist does. Some of the best memories I have are when I stumbled into places where I had to use a lot of hand gestures while struggling to communicate. In a weird way I think I connected more personally with these people than the ones who spoke English. It was like our shared awkwardness was in some way also an ice breaker. At least for me, the people I’m with and the people I meet make a vacation more memorable than the sites I see. So, wine tourists, I say be awkward and take the path less traveled!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 02:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2014/adios-penedes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2014/adios-penedes/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Greetings from Penedès. Day 6.</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;inside-the-rabbit-cave&quot;&gt;Inside the Rabbit Cave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-1410461850325.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Can Rà fols dels Caus&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can Rà fols dels Caus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my arrival in Penedès I have been hearing and reading about a winery called Can Rà fols dels Caus (house of rabbit caves). As it is only 10 min. from where I’m staying in Sant Pau d’Ordal, I made a point of making a visit. I was not disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This large estate contains an eclectic mix of structures dating as far back as Roman times. Indeed, its original purpose was to provide an outpost for Roman travelers making their way between Barcelona and Tarragona. However, amongst all these historic structures its futuristic winery is what really catches the eye. A sleek mixture of stainless steel, concrete, and natural limestone (which is key to their wine’s character) that looks more like a set from a James Bond movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-1410510785746.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wine cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wine cave literally built into the limestone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still under construction, the winery’s goal is grape-to-bottle with minimal pumping. It is an awe-inspiring mix of eccentricities (2 ft. thick automatic granite doors and a 20 ft. dia. spherical stone support…that turns!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-1410510811832.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Spherical support that turns&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spherical support that turns?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with no expense spared common sense. The result of which carries right into the final product. These wines aren’t cheap. They are estate-grown, eclectic, terroir-driven, and inspiring. They are designed to provoke thought and rattle your senses. So, let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/20140910_175610.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2011 El Recollà­s&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;2011 El Recollà­s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 El Recollà­s is their most popular white wine which tips the scales at 30€…and I still bought it. I couldn’t help it. Made from a varietal I’ve never heard of called Incrocio Manzoni (out of Veneto) and French oak aged, this wine has a cornucopia of fruit flavor running the gamut of citrus, stone, and tropical topped off with vanilla and a touch of limestone minerality. It simply makes a good Chardonnay seem one dimensional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/20140910_175559.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2013 Gran Caus&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;2013 Gran Caus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, that was exciting. Now for a rosat. 2013 Gran Caus is their 100% Merlot with about 3% residual sugar. Stop. Before you start running for the hills screaming, ““No! No f#%king White Merlot!”” just read on. These grapes are picked at a slightly lower brix, destemmed, and pumped directly into cold stainless steel tanks where they are gently pumped over for two days worth of extraction prior to press and fermentation. The result is a deep-colored rosat which smells like red vines, cherries, and strawberries, but smacks your palette with a mix of tart cherry, lively acidity, limestone minerality, salinity, thyme, a slight sweetness, and a lengthy finish that fools you into thinking red vs. pink. This wine will truly make you blush ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/20140910_175620.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2006 Can Rà fols dels Caus Pedradura&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;2006 Can Rà fols dels Caus Pedradura&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a certain character to red blends I’m finding here in Penedès. The 2006 Can Rà fols dels Caus Pedradura is no exception. There seems to be a certain tobacco/licorice in all the Cabernet Sauvignon-Garnatxa blends I’ve had here. However, this wine also has a little rustic forest floor mixed with its black cherry and raspberry fruit. This 2006 could easily pass as a 2010 in California. Still ruby in color with a hint of brick around the rim. Amazing depth, finish, complexity, and chewy tannins. Yeah, I bought it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/20140910_175630.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1997 Gran Caus&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;1997 Gran Caus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, as a treat, my host David brought out a 1997 Gran Caus, a Bordeaux blend of Cabernet Franc, Cabernet Sauvignon, and Merlot. Even after 17 years this wine was just beginning to show signs of pruning, rich cocoa notes and a bit of the same rustic character of the Pedradura. I was floored by the ageability of these wines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of their wines are available in the U.S. Look for them. You won’t be disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2014 02:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2014/greetings-from-penedes-day-6/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2014/greetings-from-penedes-day-6/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Greetings from Penedès. Day 5.</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-old-world-is-new-again&quot;&gt;The Old World is New Again&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-1410337212587.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Xarel-Lo vines look similar to chardonnay&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Xarel-Lo vines look similar to chardonnay&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have long been a wine lover. However, most of my experience has been local to my home state of California. Up until recently my understanding of wine regions has been old world (Europe) vs. new world (everywhere else). Their comparison being old traditions vs. new experimentation. I’ve always taken pride in the fact that I live somewhere in the latter category. California is indeed a land of wine and viticulture experimentation. However, now that I am in the wine business and study it more globally, I as well as my colleagues are finding this old vs. new comparison no longer applies. The combination of global markets, better educated enologists and viticulturists, changing climate, the internet, as well as other factors are forcing innovation on a global scale that defies traditional thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current trip to Spain confirms this. Penedès has always been associated with Cava. Cava, in turn, has always been labeled as an affordable alternative to Champagne. This what they teach us in class and is confirmed in most wine shops worldwide. However, as I mentioned in my earlier post &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/greetings-from-penedes-day-3/&quot;&gt;during my visit to Albet I Noya&lt;/a&gt; when one actually visits these places they will see a very different world. The fact is, there is a lot of hard work being done by wine innovators across the globe that unfortunately largely goes unseen. Why? I suspect it has a lot to do with our ridiculous systems of trade, importation and distribution, as well as our own personal biases… but that’s for another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My adventures today just confirm the groundswell of innovation happening here in Spain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-1410337093562.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Basilica Santa Maria&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Basilica Santa Maria&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the day in Vila Franca. I lovely village in the heart of Penedès that was celebrating its Catalonian Fiesta when we arrived. While nearby Sant Sadurni d’Anoia is the home of Cava, Vila Franca boasts a new Penedès wine museum called the “Vinseum” which is immediately adjacent to its famous Basilica Santa Maria. When visiting Penedès wine country I highly recommend you make this your first stop…yes it includes wine tasting. More importantly, it has an exhaustive amount of local wine making, viticulture, history, and business information and artifacts presented in a modern multimedia format. An educational primer that will get you started and is well worth the 7â‚¬.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-14103826751521.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Ancient amphoras&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ancient amphoras&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-1410382693160.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Early spreader for “Bordeaux mixture”&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Early spreader for “Bordeaux mixture,” which was a lovely anti-fungal cocktail of chemicals&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, on to wine tasting. I tasted several wines there and this is where I complete my reference to innovation. I didn’t taste any Cava. Instead, I tasted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-1410336817709.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;organic, unfiltered 100% Macabeu&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;organic, unfiltered 100% Macabeu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-1410336840862.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Rosat of Merlot, Sumoll (pr. soo-MOY), Tempranillo (Ull de Llebre), and Syrah&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rosat of Merlot, Sumoll (pr. soo-MOY), Tempranillo (Ull de Llebre), and Syrah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wpid-wp-1410336861360.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;incredible 100% Cariñena (Carignan)&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;incredible 100% Cariñena (Carignan)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These wines were not only unique in varietal make up and style, but also in region as they did not all come from Penedès.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the 2013 &lt;a href=&quot;http://clotdelessoleres.com/index.php?page=the-wine&quot;&gt;Clot de les Soleres&lt;/a&gt; 100% Penedès Macabeu. Immediately, I got an understanding of where Cava gets a lot of its flavor. This wine smelled and tasted like Cava. The lack of filtration was very evident as it was a bit cloudy and actually had some visible particulates. However, the flavor was clean citrus, honeydew, a bit spritzy, and having some yeasty notes from lees contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 &lt;a href=&quot;http://janeventura.com/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Jané Ventura&lt;/a&gt; Rosat Sellecio 10 Vinyes from the north eastern edge of Penedès near Barcelona was a bit beguiling. The nice strawberry, watermelon fruit was overwhelmed by the herbal thyme and strong rose petal which made the finish a little raspy. However, one couldn’t over look the complexity offered by the eclectic mix of varietals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best of the wines I tasted at the Vinseum was the 2011 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vinsdeltros.com&quot;&gt;Vins del Tros&lt;/a&gt; Tremenda. Cariñena is a favored grape in Catalonia and is used a lot in Priorat. This wine came out of a little-known DO called Terra Alta which lies just south of Priorat. The warmth of this region was reflected in its 15.5% alcohol. However, this was somewhat balanced by its mouth watering acidity and firm tannins. The fruit of tart currants was countered by strong tobacco and licorice. This wine is a yin-yang of extremes held in tenuous balance that both excites the palette…and makes it a little nervous.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 02:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2014/greetings-from-penedes-day-5/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2014/greetings-from-penedes-day-5/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
